<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
        "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
        <!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "../../Reference_Guide.ent">
        %BOOK_ENTITIES;
        ]>
<section id="sect-Reference_Guide-Configuration_Of_Custom_Data_Validators" role="NotInToc">
  <title>Configuration of custom data validators</title>
  <para>&PRODUCT; includes a user-configurable validator that can be applied to input fields of different bundled
    portlets. Currently, this validator is only used to configure the validation of username formats in the user
    account and user registration portlets, though the architecture allows for configurable validation
    to be used in different contexts if needed.
  </para>
  <para>The validator can be configured via properties in the <filename>configuration.properties</filename> file in the GateIn
    configuration directory. By default, this directory is found at <filename>$PLF-3.5-JBOSS_HOME/server/default/conf/gatein/</filename> if you
    are using JBoss Application Server or <filename>$PLF-3.5-TOMCAT_HOME/gatein/conf/</filename> if you are using Tomcat.
  </para>
  <para>The architecture supports several configurations that can be activated and associated to specific instances of
    the user-configurable validator when they are created and assigned to fields in portlets. We will only concern ourselves
with the currently supported use case, which is the user name validation during account creation.
  </para>

  <section id="sect-Reference_Guide-Configuration_Of_Custom_Data_Validators-Validator_Configuration">
    <title>Validator configuration</title>
    <para>A configuration is created by adding an entry to the <filename>configuration.properties</filename> file using the <parameter>gatein.validators.</parameter> prefix
      followed by the name of the configuration, a period '.' and the name of the validation aspect you want to
      configure. The user-configurable validator currently supports four different aspects per configuration, as
      follows, where <parameter>{configuration}</parameter> refers to the configuration name:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><parameter>gatein.validators.{configuration}.length.min</parameter>: The minimum length of the validated field.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><parameter>gatein.validators.{configuration}.length.max</parameter>: The maximum length of the validated field.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><parameter>gatein.validators.{configuration}.regexp</parameter>: The regular expression to which values of the validated field must
          conform.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        <parameter>gatein.validators.{configuration}.format.message</parameter>: The information message to display when
        the value does not conform to the specified regular expression. 
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  
  <section id="sect-Reference_Guide-Configuration_Of_Custom_Data_Validators-Username_Validator_Configuration">
    <title>Configuration of Username Validator</title>
      <para>By default, the username will be validated as follows:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The length must be between 3 and 30 characters.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Only lowercase letters, numbers, undescores (_) and period (.) can be used.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>No consecutive undescores (_) or period (.) can be used.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Must start with a lowercase letter.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Must end with a letter or number.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    <note>
      <para>Some components that leverage GateIn depend on usernames being all lowercase. Therefore, you are strongly
        recommended to use a lowercase username only.
      </para>
    </note>
    
   <para>If you want to make sure that your users use an email address as their username, you could use the following
      configuration:
    </para>
    <programlisting># validators
gatein.validators.username.regexp=^[A-Za-z0-9._%+-]+@[A-Za-z0-9.-]+\.[A-za-z]{2,4}$
gatein.validators.username.format.message=Username must be a valid email address
    </programlisting>
    When the username field does not conform to this rule, the account is not created and there will be a warning message.
    <programlisting>
    The field "User Name" must match the format "Username must be a valid email address".
    </programlisting>
    In case you do not define <parameter>gatein.validators.username.format.message</parameter>, the value of <parameter>gatein.validators.username.regexp</parameter> will be used in the warning message and you will see 
    <programlisting>
    The field "User Name" must match the format "^[A-Za-z0-9._%+-]+@[A-Za-z0-9.-]+\.[A-za-z]{2,4}$".
    </programlisting>
    when the username does not match the validation pattern.
  </section>
  <section id="sect-Reference_Guide-Configuration_Of_Custom_Data_Validators-Developer_Information">
    <title>Developer information</title>
    <para>The user-configurable validator is implemented by the
      <methodname>org.exoplatform.webui.form.validator.UserConfigurableValidator</methodname> class.</para>
    <para>To use a specific validator configuration to validate a given field value, add the validator to the field
      where <parameter>configurationName</parameter> is a <parameter>String</parameter> representing the name of the configuration used:
    </para>
    <programlisting>addValidator(UserConfigurableValidator.class, configurationName);</programlisting>
    <para>The validator instance can then be configured by adding the relevant information in <filename>configuration.properties</filename>,
      for example:
    </para>
    <programlisting># validators
gatein.validators.configurationName.length.min=5
gatein.validators.configurationName.length.max=10
gatein.validators.configurationName.regexp=^u\d{4,9}$
gatein.validators.configurationName.format.message=This value must start with ''u'' and be followed by 4 to 9
digits
    </programlisting>
    <para>Alternatively, a resource key can also be passed to the <methodname>addValidator</methodname> method to specify which localized message
      should be used in case a validation error occurs, for example, <parameter>configurationName</parameter> as follows:
    </para>
    <programlisting>addValidator(UserConfigurableValidator.class, configurationName, localizationKey);
    </programlisting>
    where <parameter>localizationKey</parameter> is defined in a resource bundle.
  </section>
</section>
